in this video we're going to be
continuing on with our weather
derivative series and here we'll be
actually using our modified einstein
ulembek process to simulate temperature
paths this is going to be under the
physical probability measure
of which we've estimated our market
parameters for this oh
process
so now that we've got our volatility
model we're going to be using the
s-spline for a given a particular day
within the year we've got non-constant
volatility so we're going to be
incorporating that in our model so
without further ado let's get into it so
just a recap of what we're doing in this
series we're going to go through a quick
summary on the weather derivative
contract features so the aim is with
that we want to price a temperature
option and then the underlying is either
heating degree days or cooling degree
days index over a given period of time
so the underlying of a temperature
option is this heating degree day
cooling degree day and the approximation
of average temperature in reference to a
base or reference temperature so for
daily average temperature really it's
just a proxy so you take the t max and
you add the t min and you take the
average of these two temperatures
so our underlying is daily average
temperature as per this approximation
our degree days for any given day in
period and periods we have the heating
degree
day for a given
day n is equal to
the temperature ref minus the t
temperature of that day so the daily
average temperature and the max function
so it's either if this is above zero
then it's this value or it's zero
so then we have um for a cooling degree
day we've got the temperature the daily
average temperature minus the t ref and
of course if that's positive you take
that value or
it's zero otherwise
so the payoff function here the buyer of
an option will receive an amount where
we
estimate it as ips along here equals a
function that you can define of these
heating degree or cooling degree days so
the degree days um is equal to either h
n for heating degree seasons or uh cn
for cooling degree seasons so this is
just the summation of the heating degree
days and the cooling degree days for the
entire region
that you're investigating the entire
period
so the typical seasons for otc
is
the 15th of may to the 15th of september
for cooling degree seasons or the 15th
of december the 15th of march for
heating degree seasons if you're in the
us
popular payoff functions we've got a
call with a cap
so here we have this
minimum between the cap or this payoff
function here and you'll note that the
payoff function has our degree days
minus the strike for the call and it's
the max of that um so it's either that
value or zero depending if this is
positive or negative and then we've got
this pay rate alpha so this is like the
tick value per degree day and this is
often either 2
500 or 5 000 us dollars
so now that we've gone through that
quick summary let's go into the
temperature modeling so everything that
we have done so far in this series has
been under the physical probability
measure p including including and
especially the parameter estimate
estimation of the following model
so if you remember we have our uh max
temp in our mintemp data frames of which
we've manipulated to get our daily
average temperature so if we just print
that out then you see that we get this
data frame where we just have
temperatures for a given day since 1859
january the first
so our modified mean reverting hornstein
umbeck process here we've actually
modeled and defined our parameters so
we've got this mean reverting process as
per temperature and we have a
daily average temperature denoted by
this t bar now t bar we've actually
defined as this sinusoidal model um a
fourier series of of order one and we've
been able to manipulate it so that we
actually have it just in terms of the
sine function we've defined these
parameters with omega being the period
uh 2 pi over
365.25 and the 0.25 is important because
we have such a large period of data that
it does matter about leap years
so we've got our function for the
average temperature for a given period
and then we need the uh the first
differential of this t bar and that can
just be taken by uh the derivative with
respect to time of this function t bar
now it's important to note here that t
is actually
the first ordinal number zero on the
date the first of january not 1859.
so now if we just show you what that
model looks like we've got our t model
defined here with all our parameters and
we've got our dt model so our derivative
of
t bar here
and here i've got my t bar params in
this
this list here now if i fit this model
uh across my data now um and then i
actually pass through that
those t-bar parameters into our t model
then we can actually print out that and
see the model fit so here this model is
our t-bar the average daily temperature
as we go through for each particular day
now if you remember we noticed that
variance was non-constant throughout
these periods here in the peaks of
summer and the lows of winter we have
more spread around our data so that's
why volatility is non-constant within
seasons so to come up we come around
that we had a volatility of temperature
process and that was estimated on the
based on quadratic variation so sigma
squared of our temperature process t uh
t
t for a given day so here our volatility
estimator is denoted by this formula
here based on quadratic variation so our
standard deviation of our temperature
process we then need to fit some kind of
model to this
now for this particular model i've
chosen to use a spline with five knots
and if you don't know why we chose that
please go through the previous video
where we looked at different volatility
models
to try and estimate this volatility
either given days or using the first
ordinal number from 1859 january 1st
so here i've just printed out what that
looks like for each day and the year we
see we've got non-constant volatility
and we've just done a spline fit with
five knots and it kind of looks like a
polynomial there
so now that we have our volatility and
our
sde defined in our model what we want to
do is simulate our temperature paths now
the way we're going to have to do this
is we need to break apart our sde our
modified
ornstein ulenbach process using a euler
scheme approximation
so here
just using finite differences
we've taken that the next temperature
step is equal to the current temperature
plus the derivative of t bar
plus by kappa which is that mean
reversion constant that we've estimated
um times by the difference between t bar
minus the previous temperature
plus our sigma which is our standard
deviation our volatility metric times by
a normal distribution
error term so that's z i
so what i can do is i can just define
this exact function using
a python function called euler
underscore step
here this is going to be a pandas
function so i'm going to import for
every row in our data frame
i need parameters kappa and then the
number of simulations that we're doing
here i'm just going to export
temperature which is going to be the
simulated next day temperature
so
because i need the previous temperature
t-bar in this series i'm going to need
to check if there is a previous
temperature series so if there is not
um if the t-bar shift that i'm going to
define below is not equal to
n a
then i need to define that my initial
temperature is t bar you can just set
the initial temperature to whatever you
want in the series you could assign it
randomly but i've just said that it's
the average temperature at the start of
the period
otherwise we're going to define our
current temperature as the previous
temperature
average temperature series
so
our t deterministic component is going
to be our ti our previous temperature
plus our derivative of temperature here
we've got our mean reverting term so t
underscore m rev for mean reverting and
that's just kappa times by this rho t
bar so average daily temperature minus
the temperature so here we've got sigma
which is going to be our variable
component which is our volatility for a
particular day multiplied by the normal
distributed
variable so our monte carlo simulation
here we've defined quite a large
function where we're going to take in
the trading days which is just going to
be a pandas date time index of which
we're interesting in um
computing our uh our simulation over
from start to end dates we've got our
t-bar params that we're passing in for
our actual temperature model we've got
our volatility model that we've defined
so this is going to be a fitted
volatility model for each day in the
year we've got our first ordinal process
which is going to be
needed for our t-bar model
and then we've got
the default of the number of simulations
which is going to be equal to 1 and then
our kappa which again the default is the
estimated parameter that we have chosen
and again kappa which is going to be a
default of the estimated parameter that
we've estimated in previous videos for
under the physical probability measure
so the steps here is that we're going to
check the trading date series and is it
a date time index if yes we're going to
map this to an ordinal number because
that's what we need for our model
now we're going to use the modified
ornstein ombeck process with the
estimated parameters to simulate our
t-bar our daily average temperature
and then we're going to use the
derivative of the modified uh enzyme
euler process to calculate the change of
t-bar
once we've got those two columns we can
create a data frame with this
information
and then we're going to actually extract
which day of the year it is
from our index so we'll take our data
series index
with our ordinal numbers and we'll get
the day of the year
once we've done that we can apply the b
spline for our volatility model based on
the day um the season of the year so
we're going to get a column with our
volatility for each individual day
then we're going to take a shift of the
t-bar by one day so this is the lagged
t-bar series and we need this so we can
create our euler step
now we can apply that eulerstep pandas
function that we created above
by just passing our eulerstep function
and the arguments that we've defined in
this function so kappa and then m
now we create the final data frame for
all simulations and this is just where
we pass out the information that we've
calculated
i'm going to return two data frames
one is going to be the temperature with
all those individual components t-bar
t-bar shift the day is the volatility
and then one is our end simulations for
m number of simulations for each column
so i've just spoken through all that
code but let's actually take a look at
what that looks like so the simulation
of temperature here we finally simulate
the temperature under the physical
probability measure we're defining our
date range and the number of simulations
so here we've got number of sims equals
five and then our trading dates that
we're interested in is from the first of
september 2022 all the way to 2003 to
august 31st so the frequency is going to
be days and here i'm just
calling that monte carlo temperature
function that we defined and then i'm
extracting
the monte carlo temps and then the monte
carlo sims so the monte carlo temps data
frame is the individual components used
to simulate temperature paths in this
simulation and here's what it looks like
we've got t bar which is the average
daily temperature for a given day we've
got our dt bar which is the change in
that daily bar temperature and remember
we've used the derivative of that
modified ornstein umbeck process to
calculate this and then we've got our
respective day that we've calculated
from our ordinal index and then we've
got the volatility uh using our b spline
model
now i've created this b bar shift
because remember we need the lagged
actual t-bar to be able to calculate the
next temperature
so once we've done that for each
individual simulated path we can then
get our
respective column for that temperature
series so here i've got five simulations
uh one through to five
for our temperature series for the given
date time index
so what does that look like let's plot
using that plot lib for an individual
simulation here what i've done in blue
i've got just that simulation number one
the first simulation and then i'm
plotting t-bar from our mc temps so you
can see
what the average daily temperature was
and where the variation is and here you
can see that it's very constant
consistent sorry
with our actual data now what you might
want to do is actually validate your
model in that it holds with your
estimated parameter given your real
world data you could do this in any way
you could have kept
some out of sample data that you didn't
estimate your parameters on and then
cross reference or use some kind of root
mean squared error or the like to be
able to validate your model i'm not
going to do that here because our focus
is on actually valuing weather
derivatives
now one final comment i'll make here is
that the temperature distributions are
often important to look at and i wanted
to show you the difference between our
monte carlo simulation temperature and
distributions of the peaks of summer
versus the peaks of winter
so here in australia
we've got
110 000 temperatures on the first of
july uh 2023 which is for winter and
then we've got our peak of summer which
is the first of january uh 2023. you can
debate whether those are the peaks or
not uh if you're from australia but who
cares they're really the peaks of winter
and uh and summer
so what we expect is to see quite
different um aspects of volatility uh
between these two periods
so we're simulating 10 000
different temperatures
all on the same day
so if we plot that out and we also
include the t-bar for summer and winter
we can see the difference between these
distributions
and you can see that the actual standard
deviation around these t-bars
in these histograms are quite different
between winter and summer
so now that we've actually learned how
you can
perform this
monte carlo simulation using our
modified einstein ultimate process under
the physical probability measure
now we're going to go ahead in the next
video and actually use this alter it for
risk neutral pricing approach under the
q measure
and then be able to price our weather
derivatives so as always thank you very
much for listening and i'll see you guys
in the next one
[Music]
you